Guide to the papers of Oleksii Balabas g.3
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
Oleksii Balabas papers
1915-1960
g.3
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
1.0 Linear feet 3 bound volumes, 2 boxes
This collection contains material relating to the life of Oleksii Balabas and his family in the Kuban' region of Russia, Prague, Germany, and Chicago. It includes six volumes of diaries from the 1940s and '50s, official and legal documents, correspondence, writings on Kuban' history, and photographs.
Balabas, Oleksii, 1890-1960
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 5 series as follows:
Documents
Correspondence
Writings on Kuban'
Photographs
Diaries
Scope and Contents
The Oleksii Balabas Papers contain material relating to the life of Kuban' native of Ukrainian descent Oleksii Balabas and his family in Russia, Prague, as a Displaced Person in Germany, and in Chicago. Of particular importance are six volumes of diaries in which he describes his life in Germany and Chicago and his attempts to deal with his grief over the death of his wife. In addition, the collection has official and legal documents from pre-Revolutionary Russia and his immigration into the USA, family and personal correspondence, writings on Kuban' history, and photographs from Kuban', Prague, Germany and the USA. Two letters dated 1933 from family members in Kuban' make reference to the Holodomor.
Biographical/Historical note
Oleksii Balabas was an "ordinary man" whose life encapsulates in microcosm a great deal of the history of Ukrainians in the first half of the 20th century.
He was born in 1890 in the "stantsia" Slovians'ka in Kuban' (Russian northern Caucuses). He was conscripted into the Russian Army upon the outbreak of World War I, attended cavalry school and joined as an ensign with the Slovians'ka regiment, with which he fought on the Western and Turkish fronts. After the 1917 Revolution he joined the government of the Kuban' People's Republic, associating closely with many of the top government leaders. After the takeover of the government by the monarchist "Black Hundreds" counter-revolutionaries he was arrested and exiled in 1919 to Istanbul. In 1920, he moved with his family to Prauge.
In Prague, he worked as a compositor in the print shop of the social-democratic newspaper "Právo Lidu" while furthering his education. He eventually defended a doctoral dissertation from the Charles University in Prague, and became a teacher and administrator of the Ukrainian Gymansium in Modřany.
Fleeing ahead of the Red Army in World War II, he spent time in the Karlsfeld, Füssen, and Mittenwald DP camps. He served as teacher and director of the Mittenwald camp Gymnasium. His wife Ievheniia (Pobidonostseva) died in 1947, and in 1950 he emigrated to Chicago. He worked for the Czech-language newspaper "Svernost" and taught at the Ukrainian Orthodox school. He later joined the printing establishment of Prof. Terlets'kyi where he worked as a linotype operator. He moved to New Jersey after prostate surgury, where he likely worked in the printing shop at the Ukrainian Orthodox Church of the USA in South Bound Brook.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use. Please contact the archivist (archives@ukrhec.org) for more information and to make arrangements.
Kubanʹ (Russia: Region); Exiles--Ukrainian--Czechoslovakia--Prague; Exiles--Ukrainian--Turkey--Istanbul; Immigrants--United States--Diaries; Refugee camps--Germany--Füssen; Refugee camps--Germany--Mittenwald; Ukrainian-Americans--Illinois--Chicago; Ukrainians -- Russia (Federation) -- Kubanʹ (Region); World War, 1939-1945--Refugees
- Documents, 1916-1960; Series 1.; 8 folders
  - Kuban' and Istanbul, 1916-1920; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Scope and Contents
    Russian passports, bank passbooks, deeds of sale of real estate, and a passport issued by the consulate of the Netherlands in Istanbul for transit to Prague.
  - Prague, 1923-1945; 4 folders (Box 1, Folder 3-5, Oversize 1)
    Academic documents of Oleksii and his wife, including diplomas, coursework records and student ID cards. Identification documents from the period of Nazi occupation. Certificate of appreciation from his printer colleagues.
  - Germany, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    DP worker's pass and ID cards. Newspaper clippings related to Ievheniia Balabas' death. Death certificates. Administrative correspondence regarding Gymnasium faculty position.
  - United States, 1949-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Immigration documents. Baggage tag. Immigrant Report forms and cards. Naturalization forms. Paperwork regarding request for removal to Germany. Address books. Membership cards for various organizations.
- Correspondence, 1916-1960; Series 2.; 7 folders
  - Wife and daughter, Bulk, 1919-1921; 1916-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letters from Oleksii to his wife and daughter, written from Kuban', Istanbul, Prague and Germany. Postcards from his daughter enroute from Prague to Germany.
  - Family in Kuban', Bulk, 1928-1935; 1928-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondence with family members who remained in Kuban', primarily with a Masha (Mama?) and Fenia, and later with Ievhenia Smola (his sister?), and a Zhenia (surname unknown). Two of the letters from 1933 contain allusions to the Holodomor.
  - Vladimir Chernoi, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Correspondence with Vladimir Chernoi, who may be a cousin, as he addresses himself to Oleksii as "tvoi brat" ("your brother"). Correspondence, mostly in the form of postcards, is addressed from Kuban' and Moscow.
  - Kathi Ostler, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondene with the Ostler family in Mittenwald, who may have been caring for Ievheniia's grave.
  - Vasyl' and Petro Kachurovskyi, Bulk, 1959-1960; 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondence from Balabas' son-in-law and school-age grandson after Balabas moved to New Jersey.
  - R. Lukianova, 1949-1960; 2 folders
    Correspondence with R. Lukianova (first name unknown) in Winnipeg, Manitoba.
    - Letters, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, 1949-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Portraits, group photographs, and other scenes sent to Balabas by R. Lukianova, most with extensive inscriptions on the reverse.
  - General correspondence, Bulk, 1947-1959; 1921-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Primarily personal correspondence with individuals in the USA, Canada, and the United Kingdom, as well as correspondence dating to the DP period, and some from Prague. It includes correpspondence with Alexandr Bolotenko, Ivan Fin'ko, the Holoskevych family, V. Ivanys, Maria Kasianchuk, Liudmyla Kay (his daughter), Volodymyr Korytnyk, A. Khorii (?), A. Lobachevs'kyi, Abp. Mstyslav, V. Minokov, T. V. Pucholsky, Olesiuk family, Ovcharenko family, ? Sergeiev, Selihor family, I. Varyvoda, M. Vovkodav, and others with illegible signatures.
    Arrangement
    This file is arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's surname. Materials with unknown or illegible surnames are at the end of the file.
- Writings on Kuban', Circa 1948; Series 3.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Manuscripts, newspaper clippings and correspondence related to the history of the Kuban' region.
- Photographs and postcards, 1915-1960; Series 4.; 7 folders (89 photographs, 27 postcards)
  Photographs from Kuban', Prauge, Mittenwald, and Chicago. Includes inscribed photographs sent by R. Lukianova, as well as family photographs, group pictures, and portraits.
  - Kuban' and Prague, 1915 - 1940s; 1 folder (8 photographs, 1 postcard) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Portraits, group photographs, and postcard of the Modřany Gymnasium.
  - Germany, 1945-1949; 1 folder (15 photographs) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Portraits, group photographs, and images of Mittenwald city and DP camp. Portrait card from Balabas' former students Bohdan and Volodymyr Bilan.
  - Funeral of Ievheniia Balabas, 1947; 1 folder (30 photographs, 3 negatives) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Photographs from the church service, funeral procession, and interment, as well as images of the cemetery and grave site with friends and family members.
  - United States, 1954-1960; 1 folder (18 photographs) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Portraits and group photographs of Balabas, friends, and family members.
  - Relatives and others, 1960 and undated; 1 folder (7 photographs) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Portraits (presumably of relatives) and group photographs. Only one photograph of Balabas' sister and nephew in Luga (Leningrad Oblast) is identified.
  - Postcards, 1940s - 1950s; 1 folder (26 postcards) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Blank postcards from Bavaria, Bremen, and Chicago.
- Diaries, Bulk, 1948-1959; 1920-1959; Series 5.; 3 bound volumes and 4 folders
  - Volume 1, December 1947 - May 1949
    Entries made primarily in Mittenwald, Germany.
  - Volume 2, May 1949 - March 1950
    Entries made in Mittenwald and Bremen. Also contains an entry dated March 10, 1949.
  - Volume 3, 1953
    Entries made in Chicago, IL.
  - Volume 4, March 1954 - May 1955 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Volume 5, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Volume 6, August 1957 - August 1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Entries made in Chicago, IL and South Bound Brook, NJ.
  - Loose diary pages, 1920, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Loose pages containing diary entries from 1920 (Istanbul and in transit to Prague), July 1950 - March 1951 (Chicago), December 7, 1951 (Chicago), January 14, 1955 (Chicago), January 8, 1956 (Chicago), as well as undated holograph writings.